Alright, so have you ever asked yourself the question of why Linux and why programmers seem to prefer Linux
and why Linux just seems to be really hyped among developers? This is a question that I've asked
myself in the past and especially before starting to use Linux and before starting to learn more
about Linux. And so I figured as with like most of the videos that I make on this channel that
if I've had that question in the past then there's probably a decent chance that you're having it
or have had it too. So that is the question that I'll be answering in today's video which is
why Linux. So let's go.
Oh and if you're sitting there and you're thinking where did he get that sick hoodie from,
you can get yourself one at calstore.com.
Okay, so what is it that actually makes Linux really popular among programmers? Well,
the answer is that there's actually lots of things but I'm going to go through the major ones that
I've found that are generally accepted among programmers as like what makes Linux really great
and from what I've found there's about seven things that programmers in general appreciate about
Linux. So let's go through them. The first one is security. This simply means that Linux tends to be
a safer system. So you won't need anti-virus software and viruses overall just aren't really an
issue. So it's a really secure system and you won't get bothered by needing to find and pay for
anti-virus software and then update that software and get notified by it etc. Linux just works and
is safe. The reason that Linux is really secure is because of the fact that the Linux operating system
is open source. This means that anyone who wants to can look at the source code for the system
and if you aren't familiar with this concept then this may sound like it would be the
opposite of safe since anyone can find vulnerabilities and create viruses for it or exploit the
vulnerabilities really easily and that's not wrong. Anyone can do that and a lot of people do try to
do this but the thing is that Linux is a really popular operating system and so that means that
there's so many people reading through the source code every day and like looking for these
vulnerabilities so that they can patch them themselves because of the fact that they are actually
using the system themselves so they don't want these vulnerabilities there and so they try to fix
them and so what ends up happening is that there's actually very very few of these vulnerabilities out
there and the ones that are out there it become really really hard to find because so many people
are actually looking for them and that also means that even if there are a few bad people out there
looking for these flaws and trying to exploit them in a bad way for every bad person that's out there
trying to find these flaws there's potentially like a thousand good people out there looking for
the exact same flaw and trying to eliminate it and so that kind of results in a really safe system.
The second reason is that Linux can improve your programming workflow. The package manager in Linux
is a godsend for programmers in terms of efficiency if you want to install something or use something
new just type in pseudo app get install whatever you want to use and then within a couple of seconds
or a minute or two you get it and you're ready to rock. This is something that can sometimes be
painstakingly difficult in other operating systems. First of all you need to install a package manager
in macOS and windows if you want to have a good reliable one and just doing that can be a difficult
task for a beginner with Linux that just comes pre-installed and you're ready to go and it also has
a lot of packages already installed and set up. All right so let's take a really simple example
here that kind of illustrates both point number one about security and also point number two
about ease of use and just workflow in general. So let's say that you wanted to install VLC media
player on your windows machine. What you'd have to do is you'd have to first open up a web browser
of some kind then you'd have to find or like Google search for VLC media player find the right
actual website to actually download it go to that website press the download link started
to download it run the xc file and then choose whatever like installation location and then after you've
done all that you potentially also need to restart your computer for these like changes to take
effect or for you to be able to actually use the program. Now let's say that you wanted to do
that exact same thing but in Linux all you'd have to do is open up a terminal window and type in
pseudo apt get install VLC and hit enter and then you're done. The windows approach leaves a lot
of room for errors to occur you could get to the wrong site and accidentally download malware
or you could get to the right site but accidentally press one of the thousands of download now buttons
that is actually an ad for something completely different compared to Linux where you just type it
in and it automatically does everything for you making sure to get it from the right source so you
won't accidentally get the wrong thing or malware as a programmer we usually work with lots of
different technologies and we're installing things constantly to get things to work so making the
process of installing stuff as easy and safe as possible is really important and Linux does this
really well. Oh and while we're on the topic this video is sponsored by kite. Kite is a free
auto completion engine that uses machine learning to provide the completions which is what makes it
stand out and also what makes it the best auto completion engine that I've used. One of the most
useful features is that kites completions are sorted or ranked by relevance instead of by popularity
or by the alphabet. This is possible because they're using machine learning to provide the completions.
It means that you will get suggested completions based on the code that you're actually writing and if
you're writing code in Python the co-pilot feature offers documentation look up so you don't have to
constantly google search function signatures and call patterns. With kite you can actually write
code up to 18% faster and who doesn't want to write code faster right so I highly recommend that
you download kite and try it out it's completely free and supports up to 13 programming languages
and 16 IDEs so just give it a go I know that you will like it because I love it. The third reason is
no rebooting. This is something that I touched on in the previous point when I was explaining about
how installing something in windows might work and how at the end of that process you might end up
having to restart the entire computer just to be able to work with whatever it was you installed
and this is not the case with linux and in fact with linux it's to the point where you can update the
entire operating system without having to actually reboot and this is neither possible with macOS
nor with windows and it's something that I think is really important because of the fact that as a
programmer we tend to install lots of different things and so the ability to just be able to install
something without then having to reboot the entire machine for those changes to take effect
is something that I think is really important. When doing research for this video I found an article
on tech mint that talks about why linux is often used for servers and this no rebooting point was
one of the reasons according to the article why linux is used for servers this is something that they
touch on in a part of the article where they talk about the fact that linux is built for stability
and reliability. Many linux servers on the internet have been running for years without failure
or even being restarted. The fourth reason is that linux actually comes with a ton of really powerful
programming tools pre-installed things like grip, wget, cron and lots of other things that once you
learn how they work can be extremely powerful tools that again can help you improve your workflow.
This is a point that's highly individual and it really depends on your specific use case because
there's so many pre-installed tools that come with linux and it also depends on what specific
distro of linux you choose to go with because certain distros come with certain extra tools like
collie linux for instance comes with a lot of hacking specific tools and so going through all of that
would be an entire standalone video series and I may do that in the future but I won't do that for
now but what I will do is I will leave a link in the description to an article that I found on a
Ubuntu pit where they go through some of the most commonly used tools in linux and what they're
really useful for so if you feel like learning a little bit more about these tools you can check that out.
Number five on our list is task automation. linux is almost built for automation of tasks. I'm not
an advanced user yet I'm still learning and exploring the wonders of linux but more experienced
linux users who also know how to code rarely need to do anything twice because of the fact that linux
lends itself really well for automation a pretty common thing in the linux community is something
referred to as one liners which is often used to refer to short little scripts that you write to
automate a task you may find yourself doing three things in a row every morning as you start up
your computer maybe you always open up Spotify to play a certain playlist and then you open up your
latest project that you're working on and then you open up Discord by the way check out our
Discord community link in the description with linux it's very easy to write a quick little
script to automate all of these tasks with a simple cron job or something like that there are lots
of pre-installed tools like we talked about in our previous point that lend themselves really
well to automation the sixth point is performance and no linux is not necessarily faster than any other
operating system but it is very lightweight for an OS and it's compatible with pretty much any
machine you can find you can run linux on almost anything so this means that you can very often
take an old laptop that is virtually useless because of being so slow and install linux on that
machine and all of a sudden breathe new life into that a machine that was impossible to work with
before is now all of a sudden working really well there are more performance benefits of linux like
the reliability of the systems and other things like that but I feel like this is like the major one
like being able to revive a dead computer is something that's really useful I think and it's
also really like environmentally friendly because it means that your laptop running linux will last
you so much longer than one running macOS or windows okay so number seven is a bit of an odd one
but it is that linux actually provides you with useful error messages this may sound a little
weird or whatever but it is really important because with windows and macOS where you can often
find yourself stuck with it's an error message along the lines of like oops something went wrong
and it's not very useful because like googling that and like finding the actual answer to that
question is really difficult because lots of different other people have had that same error
message for lots of different things but with linux instead what you'll get is a full readout
of the actual processes and you'll get like proper you'll actually see what actually happened
and that means that it's way easier to actually google that and find an answer to your specific
problem and that is something that's really important especially for programmers when you're
running into these errors constantly now this also comes with a caveat that a beginner might not
find that much help from these error messages at least not if they've never spent time in a terminal
like interface because for a beginner this can be very intimidating and just seem like a bunch
of text that all says the same thing but once you've spent some time in a terminal these error
messages are super useful all right so secret point number eight this is one that i didn't really
want to include in the main seven points because of the fact that i don't think that it quite
belongs in the seven points i don't think that it's a good reason to choose linux over windows
and macOS but i do think that it's a reason that a lot of linux users kind of like to use so i
wanted to include it in the list anyway and so point number eight is customization and the thing
about linux is that you can pretty much customize anything and because of the fact that it's open
source you can essentially like it's limitless because you can write your own customizations for it
so you can really actually customize everything and i think that this is something that programmers
tend to care about a lot like customizations and making your environment your own so i think
that it's something that's really important to programmers but like i said i don't think that
it's a reason to choose linux over macOS or windows it's not an actual benefit it's just like a
appearance benefits i guess there could be like benefits of it where you set up the environment to
be more productive for you because you can customize certain things but overall i don't think that it's
a major point to why you should choose linux over windows and macOS but yeah it is a really
interesting point and once you start going down the rabbit hole that is like linux customization
you'll quickly realize that you can spend an entire lifetime there all right so in conclusion
there really aren't that many things that you can do on linux that are impossible to do on other
systems especially if compared with macOS but the overarching theme is ease of use as a rule it's
easier to do what you want to do on linux than it is to do on other operating systems so should you
switch to linux the answer that i like to give here is that you should probably try out linux first
in a virtual machine and then see what you think of it and then you can kind of go from there
because that's what i did that's how i got started i started out with a virtual machine
and then after a while i just found myself spending more and more time there than i did in my main
OS and especially for like programming related tasks that was just so much smoother to do in linux
than it was to do in my main OS at the time and so that's kind of my advice that's how i would go
about it and yeah that's it for this one i hope i was able to answer the question of why program
ers tend to use linux over other operating systems and yeah that's it for this one i hope you enjoyed it
i hope i'll see you in the next one